Finding Aid for W. B. Hinsdale papers, 1893-1942 (bulk 1922-1938)
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
W. B. Hinsdale papers 1893-1942 1922-1938
Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.
851538 Aa 2 UAm
Often termed the father of Michigan archaeology, Wilbert B. Hinsdale developed and cared for the collections of the Great Lakes Division of the Museum of Anthropology at the University of Michigan from 1922 to 1944, after retiring from his position as Dean of the Homeopathic Medical College. The papers contain correspondence, topical files related to archaeological subjects, site files for archaeological sites throughout Michigan, and personal scrapbooks, diaries, and photographs.
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
4.25 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were received in several accessions. The original accessions (donor no. 1278 and 1427 1427) arrived in 1944. The most recent accession was transferred by the Museum of Anthropology (donor no. 9273 9273) in 2003.
Restricted access in part. Information on the location of archaeological sites in Michigan is protected against disclosure under an Attorney General's opinion and is exempt from Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests. Site information is present in boxes 3, 4 and 5 of the Hinsdale papers. For information on petitioning for access to site file information, please consult the reference archivist.
Wilbert B. Hinsdale was born on May 25, 1851 in Wadsworth, Ohio. He received a B.S. from Hiram College in 1875 and an M.S. in 1878. Hinsdale received an M.D. from Cleveland Homeopathic Medical College in 1887. He received an A.M. from Hiram College in 1897. Hinsdale served on the staff of the Cleveland Homeopathic Medical College from 1890 to 1895.
In 1895 Hinsdale was appointed Professor of Materia Medica, Therapeutics, and Clinical Medicine (later Internal Medicine) and dean of the Homeopathic Medical College at the University of Michigan. He was later given the additional title of director of the Homeopathic Medical Hospital. He retired from both positions in 1922, after the college was essentially dissolved by a mandated merger with the university's Medical School.
Although he was a doctor by profession, Hinsdale had a lifelong interest in archaeology, and even before the Museum of Anthropology was established, he deposited a large collection of Native American artifacts with the university. Soon after his retirement in 1922, Hinsdale was given the honorary title of custodian in charge of the collections in Michigan Archaeology. His charge was to develop the university's collections with funding from the Museum of Zoology. After the Museum of Anthropology was established, Hinsdale's title was changed to Associate in Charge of the Great Lakes Division in 1931.
Affectionately termed the father of Michigan archaeology by his colleagues, Hinsdale was responsible for the first systematic attempts to identify, organize and record the prehistory of the state of Michigan. His extensive network of "informants" (mainly amateur archaeologists) provided him with a continual stream of information about archaeological sites and finds across the state. Hinsdale also visited many sites and led the earliest Museum of Anthropology-sponsored fieldwork in the state. Hinsdale's Archaeological Atlas of Michigan, published in 1931, brought together information about the location of Michigan sites throughout the state for the first time, and was an important resource for professional and amateur archaeologists alike. Other notable archaeological publications include The First People of Michigan (G. Wahr, 1930), The Indians of Washtenaw County, Michigan (G. Wahr, ca. 1927) and Distribution of the Aboriginal Population of Michigan (University of Michigan Press, 1932). Hinsdale was also involved in the development of two important anthropological associations in the state, the Michigan Archaeological Society and the Anthropology Section of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters.
Hinsdale married Estella Stone in 1875. They had one son, Albert. Hinsdale's brother, Burke Aaron Hinsdale (1837-1900) was a well-known educator. Burke Hinsdale served as the president of Hiram College, was a professor in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts at the University of Michigan, wrote one of the earliest histories of the university, and was a personal friend of U.S. President James A. Garfield. Wilbert Hinsdale died on July 25, 1944 in Ann Arbor.
(Additional information on W.B. Hinsdale and other members of his family is available in the Bentley Library's vertical file and the Hinsdale Family Papers.)
The W.B. Hinsdale Papers consist of five series: Personal, Correspondence, Topical Files, Writing and Michigan Site Files.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Great Britain.; Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.; Homeopathy--Michigan.; Medicine--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Hospital.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Medical School.; University of Michigan. Museum of Anthropology.; Archaeology.; Excavations (Archaeology)--Michigan.; Michigan--Antiquities.; Indians of North America--Michigan.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923.; Hussey, Ethel Fountain, 1865-1915.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Thompson, William Oxley, 1855-1933.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.; Club (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Field notes.; Scrapbooks.
- Personal
  The Personal series, 1893-1938 (1.5 linear feet), includes material related to Hinsdale's family and work lives. The series contains seven scrapbooks, a travel diary and related notebook from a trip to the British Isles in 1905, a notebook of social callers to Hinsdale's home from 1927 to 1932, personal correspondence, photographs and miscellaneous mementos. Several of the scrapbooks relate to Hinsdale's tenure with the Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital, and include newspaper clippings, programs from events, correspondence, and extracts from college bulletins.
  - Catalogue Notebook for W.B. Hinsdale Artifact Collection undated (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1909-1932 (Box 1)
  - Diary of Trip through British Isles 1905 (Box 1)
    (includes related small notebook)
  - "Leaves from a Microbe's Notebook," 1899 (Box 1)
  - Mementos 1910s-1930s (Box 1)
  - Notebook of Social Callers to Hinsdale's Home 1927-1932 (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence
    - 1896-1915 (Box 1)
    - 1933-1938, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Self-Cultivation in English by George H. Palmer, 1916 (Box 1)
    (annotated)
  - The Medicine of the Future by George Burford, 1910 (Box 1)
    (inscribed, includes 2 letters from Burford to Hinsdale)
  - Scrapbook of Articles by Albert E. Hinsdale and W.B. Hinsdale 1900-1922 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook Related to the Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital 1899-1910 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook Related to the Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital 1911-1920 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1905-1911 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of Albert E. Hinsdale 1893-1903 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1899 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook 1895-1899 (Box 2)
  - Photographs 1900s-1930s (Box 2A)
  - Large Photographs (outsize folder, call no. UAm) (Box 2A)
- Writing
  The Writing series, 1925-1936 (0.5 linear feet), includes manuscripts, background research, and correspondence related to some of Hinsdale's publications. Of particular note is a set of questionnaires sent to people around the state to collect information for Hinsdale's 1932 publication Distribution of the Aboriginal Population in Michigan.
  - Archaeological Atlas of Michigan (correspondence re:), 1929-1936 (Box 2A)
  - Distribution of the Aboriginal Population in Michigan
    - Correspondence 1932 (Box 2A)
    - Questionnaire Responses 1927-1935 (Box 2A)
  - Indian Corn Culture in Michigan, [1927] (Box 2A)
  - Indian Gazetteer (correspondence re:) 1925-1936 (Box 2A)
  - Indian Modes and Paths of Travel in Michigan, [1927] (Box 2A)
  - Indian Modes of Travel 1926, undated (Box 2A)
  - Nutritive Value of Native Indian Foods in Michigan undated (Box 2A)
  - The First People of Michigan, [1930] (Box 2A)
  - The Indians of Washtenaw County, [1927] (Box 2A)
- Correspondence
  [Access to these portions of these files is restricted; please contact the reference archivist for further information.]
  The Correspondence series, 1922-1942 (0.75 linear feet) contains incoming and outgoing professional correspondence related to Hinsdale's post-retirement work in archaeology. The correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and much of it relates to archaeological sites and projects in Michigan. Of particular note are the folders for Walter Schmidt, William F. Gagnieur, Emerson Greenman, and Margaret Lambert which include substantial archaeological and ethnographic field notes.
  - A 1927-1938 (Box 3)
    [Restricted]
  - Brock, Mrs. L.P. 1924-1929 (Box 3)
  - B 1924-1940 (Box 3)
  - C 1927-1942 (Box 3)
  - D 1932-1940 (Box 3)
  - E 1932-1940 (Box 3)
  - Fox, George R. 1922-1929 (Box 3)
  - F 1924-1940 (Box 3)
  - Gagnieur, William F. 1932-1937 (Box 3)
  - Greenman, Emerson 1932-1938 (Box 3)
  - G 1929-1940 (Box 3)
  - Hiram College 1928-1938 (Box 3)
  - Hosack, Harry 1932-1934 (Box 3)
  - H 1925-1939 (Box 3)
  - I-J 1927-1938 (Box 3)
  - K 1927-1940 (Box 3)
  - Lambert, Margaret 1936-1938 (Box 3)
  - L 1924-1938 (Box 3)
  - Ma-Me 1927-1940 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Department of Conservation 1929-1938 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Historical Commission 1922-1935 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Legislature 1924-1929 (Box 3)
  - Moorehead, Warren K. 1922-1933 (Box 3)
  - Mi-Mz 1924-1938 (Box 3)
  - N-O 1922-1938 (Box 3)
  - Ohio State Archaeological and Historical Society 1929-1936 (Box 3)
  - P 1927-1937 (Box 3)
  - R 1925-1938 (Box 3)
  - Schmidt, Walter 1923-1938, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Smith, Harlan I. 1923-1932 (Box 3)
  - State Historical Society of Wisconsin 1924-1930 (Box 3)
  - Stevens, Edward J. 1923-1924 (Box 3)
  - S 1923-1938 (Box 4)
  - T 1925-1936 (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan 1923-1938 (Box 4)
  - Vreeland, F.M. 1932-1937 (Box 4)
  - V 1924-1938 (Box 4)
  - W-Y 1925-1939 (Box 4)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series, 1915-1938 (0.75 linear feet), includes correspondence, reports, photographs, and other materials related to particular subjects. Most of the files relate to Hinsdale's archaeological work, including a large span of geographic files that provide information on sites, artifacts, and collectors. The series is particularly strong in information about Michigan collectors and collections. One folder of material related to the Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital is also included in the series.
  - Agricultural Activities 1926-1935 (Box 4)
  - Archaeology Notebooks undated (Box 4)
  - Arizona-Artifacts 1924-1930 (Box 4)
  - Bird-Stones 1928-1936 (Box 4)
    (includes photos)
  - Canada 1928-1937 (Box 4)
  - Cemeteries and Burial Grounds 1923-1934 (Box 4)
  - Central America 1923 (Box 4)
  - Earthworks and Mounds 1923-1937 (Box 4)
  - Europe-Germany 1927 (Box 4)
  - Field Work 1935-1936 (Box 4)
  - Firearms Inventory undated (Box 4)
  - Florida 1930 (Box 4)
  - Grand Traverse Region 1920s (Box 4)
    (notebook)
  - Homeopathic Medical College and Hospital 1910-1931 (Box 4)
  - Illinois 1922-1933 (Box 4)
  - Indian Informants 1926 (Box 4)
  - Indian People 1932 (Box 4)
  - Indian Place Names 1929-1936, undated (Box 4)
  - Indiana-Artifacts 1927-1930 (Box 4)
  - Indiana-Sites 1930-1938 (Box 4)
  - Indiana-Trepanning 1927-1932 (Box 4)
  - Maps (including correspondence related to maps) 1922-1938, undated (Box 4)
  - Medals 1935 (Box 4)
  - Michigan
    - Agriculture 1922-1928 (Box 4)
    - Artifacts
      - Baskets, Bones, Canoes, Horn, Ivory, Teeth 1924-1932 (Box 4)
      - Brass, Copper, Silver 1924-1949 (Box 4)
      - Pottery, Shell, Beads 1927-1937 (Box 4)
      - Slate and Stone 1924-1938 (Box 4)
    - Collectors, Collections
      - Donations 1915-1938, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Donors 1922-1937 (Box 4)
      - Donors-C.W. Manktelow 1922-1938 (Box 4)
    - History 1931-1936 (Box 4)
    - Human Remains, Burials 1923-1931 (Box 4)
    - Indian Industries 1929-1934, undated (Box 4)
    - Indian Mines, Quarrying, Stoneworking 1922-1938 (Box 4)
    - Indian Trails, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Informants (re: Indians) 1934-1937 (Box 4)
    - Museums 1927-1937 (Box 4)
    - Publishers, Press 1923-1930 (Box 4)
    - Sites 1924-1931, undated (Box 4)
    - Skulls, Skeletal Material 1934-1936 (Box 5)
    - Trepanning, Medicine 1924-1937 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota 1926-1936 (Box 5)
  - New Jersey 1922 (Box 5)
  - New Mexico 1926-1929 (Box 5)
  - New York
    - Museums 1923-1937 (Box 5)
    - Sites and Artifacts 1923-1935 (Box 5)
  - Ohio 1927-1931 (Box 5)
  - Panama 1922, undated (Box 5)
  - Pennsylvania 1929-1938 (Box 5)
  - Personnel 1934 (Box 5)
  - Photographs (correspondence re:) 1924-1934 (Box 5)
  - Rackham Fund 1935-1936 (Box 5)
  - Songs and Legends 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - South America 1927 (Box 5)
  - South Dakota 1924, undated (Box 5)
  - Tennessee 1922-1928 (Box 5)
  - Trails 1927, undated (Box 5)
  - Washington, D.C. 1922-1928 (Box 5)
  - Wisconsin 1922-1936 (Box 5)
- Michigan Site Files 1920s-1930s
  The Michigan Site Files, 1920s-1930s (0.75 linear feet), are organized alphabetically by county and include index cards, correspondence, and other information related to archaeological sites in Michigan. Most of the information dates from the 1920s and 1930s.
  - Alcona County (Box 5)
  - Alger County (Box 5)
  - Allegan County (Box 5)
  - Alpena County (Box 5)
  - Antrim County (Box 5)
  - Arenac County (Box 5)
  - Baraga County (Box 5)
  - Barry County (Box 5)
  - Bay County (Box 5)
  - Benzie County (Box 5)
  - Berrien County (Box 5)
  - Branch County (Box 5)
  - Calhoun County (Box 5)
  - Cass County (Box 5)
  - Charlevoix County (Box 5)
  - Cheboygan County (Box 5)
  - Chippewa County (Box 5)
  - Clinton County (Box 5)
  - Delta County (Box 5)
  - Eaton County (Box 5)
  - Emmet County (Box 5)
  - Genesee County (Box 5)
  - Gogebic County (Box 5)
  - Grand Traverse County (Box 5)
  - Gratiot County (Box 5)
  - Hillsdale County (Box 5)
  - Huron County (Box 5)
  - Ingham County (Box 5)
  - Ionia County (Box 5)
  - Iosco County (Box 5)
  - Iron County (Box 5)
  - Isabella County (Box 5)
  - Jackson County (Box 5)
  - Kalamazoo County (Box 5)
  - Kalkaska County (Box 5)
  - Kent County (Box 5)
  - Keweenaw County (Box 5)
  - Lake County (Box 5)
  - Lapeer County (Box 5)
  - Leelanau County (Box 5)
  - Lenawee County (Box 5)
  - Livingston County (Box 5)
  - Mackinac County (Box 5)
  - Macomb County (Box 5)
  - Manistee County (Box 5)
  - Marquette County (Box 5)
  - Mason County (Box 5)
  - Mecosta County (Box 5)
  - Menominee County (Box 5)
  - Midland County (Box 5)
  - Monroe County (Box 5)
  - Montmorency County (Box 5)
  - Muskegon County (Box 5)
  - Newaygo County (Box 5)
  - Oakland County (Box 5)
  - Oceana County (Box 5)
  - Ontonagon County (Box 5)
  - Oscoda County (Box 5)
  - Otsego County (Box 5)
  - Ottawa County (Box 5)
  - Presque Isle County (Box 5)
  - Saginaw County, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - St. Clair County (Box 5)
  - St. Joseph County (Box 5)
  - Sanilac County (Box 5)
  - Schoolcraft County (Box 5)
  - Shiawassee County (Box 5)
  - Tuscola County (Box 5)
  - Van Buren County (Box 5)
  - Washtenaw County (Box 5)